Fifth Semester B.E. Degree Examination, December 2012
        Database Management Systems

        PART-A

1(a).Define the following with examples:(10 Marks)
 (i) Value set (ii) Complex attribute  (iii) Data model iv) Schema v) Metadata.

(b). Explain the component module of DBMS and their interactions, with the help of a diagram.(10 Marks)

2(a).What are the structural constraints on a relationship type? Explain with examples.05 Marks)

(b).What is a weak entity type? Explain the role of partial key in design of weak entity type.

(c).Design an ER — diagram for the Movie database considering the following requirements :

(i) Each Movie is identifies by its title and year of release, it has Length in minutes and can have zero of more quotes, langCage.

(ii) Production companies are identified by Name, they have address, and each production company can produce one or more mov [es_

(iii) Actors are identified by Name and Date of Birth, they can apt in one or more movies and each actor has a role in a movie.

(iv) Directors are identified by Name and Date of Birth, so each Director can direct one or more movie and each movie can be directed by one or more Directors,

(v) Each movie belongs to any one category like Horror, action, Drama, etc.(10 Marks.)

3(a).What is meant by integrity constraint? Explain the importance of Referential integrity constraint. How Referential integrity constraint is implemented in SQL?(10 Marks)

(b).Consider the following schema and write the Relational Algebra.

    SAILORS (SID., SNAME, RATING., AGE)
    BOATS (BID, BNAME, COLOR)
    RESERVE (SID, BID, DAY).
   •
   (i) Retrieve the sailors names who have reserved red and green boats.

   (ii) Retrieve the sailors names with age over 20 years and reserved black boat.

   (iii) Retrieve the number of boats which are not reserved.

   (iv) Retrieve the sailors names who have reserved green boat on Monday_

   (v) Retrieve the sailors names who is the oldest sailor with rating 10. (10 Marks)

4(a).Consider the following schema and write the 'SQL queries

    EMP (SSN, NAME, ADDR, SALARY. SEX, DNO)
    DEP(DNO., DNAIVIE, TvIG'RSSN)
    DEP_LOCN (DNO, DLOCN)
    PROJ (PNO. PNArviE, PLOCN, DNO)
    WORKSON (SSN, PNO,NOHRS)
    DEPENDENT (SSN, DEPNTNAME„ DEPNTSEX, DEPNTRELATIONSHIP)

    (i) Retrieve the manager name with at feast 1 dependent.
    (ii) Retrieve the employee name who work on any of the project that Kumar works.
    (iii) Retrieve the pno, prii.;ime, no of man hours work done on each project.
    (iv) Retrieve the pname which are controlled by Research department
    (v) Retrieve the employee name who work for dept no. 10 and have a daughter. (10 Marks)
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                         I OCS54
(b)Consider the following schema and write the SQL queries :

    STUDENT (STUDENT_ID, SNAME, MAJOR, CPA)
    FACULTY (FACULTY_ID, FNAME, DEPT, DESIGNATION, SALARY)
    COURSE (COURSE ID, CNAME, FACULTY_I D)
    ENROLL(COURSE' ID, STUDENT. ID, GRADE)

    (i) Retrieve the student name who is studying under faculties or-`Mechanica I dept".

    (ii) Retrieve the student name who have enrolled under any of the courses in which 'Kumar' has enrolled,

    (iii)Retrieve the faculty name who earn salary which is greater than the average salary of all the faculties.

    (iv) Retrieve the Sname who are not been taught by faculty 'Kumar'.

    (v) Retrieve the faculty names who are assistant professors of computer science department,(10 Marks)

                PART-B

5(a).How is view created and dropped.? What problems are associated with updating views(08 Marks)

(b).How are triggers and assertions defined in SQL? Explain.

(c).Explain the concept of stored procedure..in brief,

6(a).Consider R ={A B C D E F} :  FD'S { A--> BC, C-->E,CD--EF}
        Show that AD--F

(b). Book_title|Auth_name | Book_type | Listprice | Affiliation | Publication I

       F DS {Book_title-->Book_type, publication
      Author_name--->Affiliation
      Book_type--->Listprice}
      Find the key and normalize.

(c).What is a set of functionai dpendencies F said to be minimal? Give an algorithm for finding a mininial cover G for F.

7(a). Consider R={A B C D E F}
       FDS{ AB-->CD ,A-->CF,B--F,BGD-->F,D-->E,DE-->F }

Find an irreducible cover for this set of FDs.(06 Marks)

(b).Explain the properties of decomposition .(06 Marks)

(c).Consider R={ A B C D E F }
        FDS {AB-->C, B-->E, A-->DF }
        Check whether decomposition is lossless.(08 Marks)

8.a. What are ACID properties? Explain(06 Marks)

b. What i a schedule? Explain with example conflict Serializable schedule(08 Marks)

c. What is two  phase locking protocol? How does it guarantee serializability?(06 Marks)


                    *****







