Fifth Semester B.F. Degree Examination, December 2012
 Systems Software

              PART — A

1(a).Explain the instruction formats and addressing modes of SIC/XE machine architecture.(10 Marks)

(b).Generate the target address for the following object codes:
     (i) 032600    (ii) 010030
   Content of X = 000090;
   Content of B = 006000:
   Content of PC = 003000  (04 Marks)

(c).Write a S1C/XE program to read 100 byte record from a device F5- into BUFFER. Use immediate and register-to-register instructions.(06 Marks)

2(a).With an algorithm explain pass-1  of a 2-pass assembler.(10 Marks)

(b).Generate the object code for each  statement and write the object programs for the following SIC/XE program.

 Given that: CLEAR =B4, LDA=00, LDB = 68, ADD=18, TIX = 2C, JLT=38, STA = 0C

   SUM    START     0
   FIRST  CLEAR     X
          LDA       #0
          +LDB      #TOTAL
          BASE      TOTAL
   LOOP   ADD       TABLE, X
          TIX       COUNT
          JLT        LOOP
          STA        TOTAL
   COUNT  RESW      1
   TABLE  RESW       2000
   TOTAL  RESW       1
          END       FIRST (10 Marks)

3(a).With required data structures and processing logic, explain the implementation of literals within an assembler.(07 Marks)

(b).What are program blocks? How multiple program blocks arc handled by an assembler?(07 Marks}

(c).Compare a two-pass assembler with a single pass assembler. How forward references are handled in one-pass assembler?(06 Marks)

4(a).Define program relocation. Explain the different ways of doing program relocation.(06 Marks)

(b).With an algorithm, explain pass 1 of a linking loader.(08 Marks)

(c).Explain the facilities available in MS-DOS linker for program linking.(06 Marks)

                         PART-B

5(a).With a neat diagram, explain the working of typical editor structure.(08 Marks)

(b).Explain the debugging functions and capabilities of an interactive debugging system.(08 Marks)

(c).List the four tasks of a document editing process.(04 Marks)

6(a).Define MACRO. Briefly explain the various data structures used in the design of MACRO  PROCESSOR.(08 Marks)

(b).With an example. explain generation of unique labels in macros.(06 Marks)

(c).Explain the advantages and disadvantages ofgeneral purpose macro proecssors.(06 Marks)

7(a).With an example, explain the structure of a LEX program.(07 Marks)

(b).Write regular expressions to identify the following:

   i) Identifier
   ii) Decimal number
   iii) -ve integer
   iv) + ve fraction  (08 Marks)

(c).Write a short note on parser-lexar communication.(05 Marks)

8(a).Define YACC tools. What are the tv,o types of conflicts in YACC? Give examples. (08 Marks)

(b).Write a YACC program to evaluate an arithmetic expression involving operators +,-, *, +.(07 Marks)

(c).Write a short note on shift/reduce parsing.(05 marks)


                *****


