Fifth Semester B.E. Degree Examination, June/July 2014
System Software

        PART — A

1(a).Explain the instruction formats and addressing modes of SIC/XE.(10 Marks)

(b).Write a program in both SIC and SIC/XE to copy a character string 'system software' to another character string.(10 Marks)

2(a).Explain the data structures and pass-1 algorithm of SIC assembler.(10 Marks)

(b).Generate the symbol table and write the object program for the following SIC/XE program:

(Given that: LDX = 04, LDA = 00, LDB = 68, ADD = 18, TIX = 2C, JLT = 38, STA = OC,RSUB = 4C).

    SUM	    START	0
    FIRST	LDX	    #0
            LDA	    #0
            +LDB	#TABLE2
            BASE    TABLE2
    LOOP	ADD	    TABLE, X
            ADD	    TABLE2, X
            TIX     COUNT
            JLT	    LOOP
            +STA	TOTAL
            RSUB
    COUNT	RESW	1
    TABLE	RESW	2000
    TABLE2	RESW	2000
    TOTAL   RESW	1
    END	    FIRST	 (10 Marks)

3(a).What are control sections? Explain how linking is performed between control sections.(10 Marks)

(b).Explain how multipass assembler handles the following forward reference:

     1  HALFSZ  EQU  MAXLEN/2
     2  MAXLEN  EQU  BUFFEND-BUFFER
     3  PREVBT  EQU  BUFFER-1
     4  BUFFER  RESB 4096
     5  BUFFEND EQU   *

Assume that, when assembler goes to line 4, location counter contains 1034(Hex).(10 Marks)

4(a).With source code, explain the working of boot-strap loader.(10 Marks)

(b).Explain machine dependent features of loader.(10 Marks)

                   PART — B

5(a).Explain the overview of editing process.(04 Marks)

(b).Explain editor structure with a diagram.(08 Marks)

(c).Explain the functions and debugging capabilities of interactive debugging system.(08 Marks)

6(a).Explain the data structures used in macro processor with example.(08 Marks)

(b).Explain machine independent features of macro processor.(12 Marks)


7(a).What are LEX and YACC? Explain the different sections of LEX with example.(10 Marks)

(b).What are regular expressions? Explain the characters used in forming regular expressions.(10 Marks)

8(a).What is shift/reduce parsing? Explain the parsing of the input "fred = 12 + 13" and represent using parse tree.(10 Marks)

(b).Explain the ambiguity in arithmetic expression. What is the ambiguity in parsing 2 + 3 x 4?
    Explain the solution for it .(10 Marks)

            *****