Fifth Semester RE. Degree Examination, December 2012
Operating Systems

        PART — A

1(a).What is a distributed operating system? What are the advantages of the distributed operating system?(06 Marks)

(b).What are system calls? With examples explain difkrent categories of system calls. (07 Marks)

(c).With a neat diagram, explain the concept of virtual machine.(07 Marks)

2(a).Explain the process state transition diagram.(06 Marks)

(b).Explain multithreading models.(09 Marks)

(c).For the processes listed below, draw Gantt charts using preemptive and non preemptive priority scheduling algorithm. A larger priority number has a higher priority.

Jobs  Arrival time  Burst time Priority
j1        0          6           4
j2        3          5           2
j3        3          3           6
j4        5          5           3

3(a).What is busy waiting in a critical section concept? How semaphore is used to solve critical section problem? What are the advantages of semaphore?(10 Marks)

(b).What is a monitor? Explain the solution to the classical dining philosopher's problem, using monitor.(10 Marks)

4(a).What is a resource allocation graph(RAG)? Explain how RAG is very useful in describing deadly embrace by considering your own example.(08 Marks)

(b).System consists of five jobs (J1, J2, J3, J4,J5) and three resources (R1, R2 R3). Resource type R1 has 10 instances, resource type R2. has 5 instances and R3 has 7 instances. The following
snapshot of the system has been taken

Jobs Allocation   Maximum
     R1 R2 R3     R1 R2 R3
J1   0   1  0      7  5  3
J2   2   0  0      3  2  2
J3   3   0  1      9  0  2
J4   2   1  1      2  2  2
J5   0   0  2      4  3  3
Available:
R1 R2 R3
3  3  2
Find need matrix and calculate the safe sequence by using Banker's algorithm. Mention the above system is safe or not sate.(O8 Marks)

(c).Briefly explain the methods for handling deadlocks.(04 Marks)

                 PART— B

5(a).Distinguish between :

  (i) Logical versus physical address space
  (ii) Paging versus segmentation
  (iii) First fit and best fit algorithms.(07 Marks)

(b).Mention the problem with simple paging scheme. How MB is used to solve this problem? Explain with supporting hardware diagram and with an example.(08 Marks)

(c).On a system using simple segmentation, compute the physical address for each of the logical address, logical address is given in the following segment table.If the address generates a segment fault, indicate it as "segment fault".

Segment    i Base    Length
   0         330      124
   1         876      211
   2         111      99
   3         498      302

  i) 0, 9, 9   ii) 2, 78
  iii) 1, 265    iv) 3, 222
  c) 0, 1 1 1 (05 Marks)

6(a).Explain briefly different file types.(04 Marks)

(b).Explain the different types of directory structures, with examples and mention their advantages and disadvantages.(08 Marks)

(c).With supporting diagrams, explain linked and indexed method of allocating disk space. (08 Marks)

7(a).Explain the following disk scheduling algorithms in brief
   (i) SS1FF   (ii) SCAN   (iii) LOOK (09 Marks)

(b).Explain in brief, the selection of a disk scheduling algorithm.(04 Marks)

(c).What is protection? Distinguish between mechanisms and policies. Explain briefly the access matrix with domains as objects.(07 Marks)

8.Write short notes on (any four):
    a. Linux history
    b. Linux design principles
    c. Components of a Linux system 
    d, Optimal page replacement algorithm 
    e. Steps in handling page fault.(20 Marks)

              *****
