Fifth Semester B.E. Degree Examination, December 2012
    Computer Networks - I

        PART — A

1(a).What is protocol? Define the key elements of protocols?(05 Marks)

(b).Define network topology, explain ring topology with advantages and disadvantages.(05 Marks)

(c).Explain the different levels of addressing used in an internet with a suitable example for each level of addressing in TCP /IP?(10 Marks)

2(a).Explain the following :(05 Marks)

(i) Bandwidth
(ii) Throughput
(iii) Transmission time
(iv) Latency
(v) Jitter.

(b).Explain with the block diagram, the causes for transmission impairments.(09 Marks)

(c).Explain with neat waveform any two polar line coding schemes.(06 Marks)

3(a).What is multiplexing? Explain with a neat diagram FDM.(08 Marks)

(b).Explain how time — division — multiplexing, differs from FDIVI, with a neat diagram? (04 Marks)

(c).What is switching? Differentiate circuit switch network with packet — switched network.(08 Marks)

4(a).What is internet checksum? List the steps undertaken. by sender and receiver for error detection.(06 Marks)

(b). Explain with an example of block coding method for error detection and correction?(10 Marks)

(c).What is the Hamming distance? Find the minimum Hamming distance of the coding scheme shown in the table.(04 Marks)

    Data word   Code Word
    0   0       0 0 0 0 0
    0   1       0 1 0 1 1
    1   0       1 0 1 0 1
    1   1       1 1 1 1 0

                    PART —B

5(a).Calculate the time takes to send 2 million hits of data in a system thal uses stop and wait protocols, if the distance between sender and receiver is 2000 kms. Assume packet size is 400 bits and propagation speed is 2 x 10a m. No data or control frame is lost  (10 Marks)

(b).Explain the frame format and transitional phases of Point-to -point protocols. (10 Marks)

6(a).Explain why collision is an issue in a random access protocol but not in controlled access or channelizing protocols?(04 Marks)

(b) Explain any two popular control access methods. with a neat diagram.(08 Marks)

(c). Explain 802.3 MAC frame format.(08 Marks)

7(a) Explain the services of IEEE 802.11 standards.(04 Marks)

(b).Write a short notes on.

     (i) Bluetooth
     (ii) Cellular telephone. (10 Marks)

(c). Explain the five standard of IMT — 2000 radio — interface of 3G systems?(06 Marks)

8(a).Explain briefly the advantages of IPV6.(06 Marks)

(b).Find out the netid and hostid of the following 1P address?

        (i)  111.64.2.6
        (ii) 131.57.9.3
        (iii) 207.64.52.11
        (iv) 225.34.2.1.   (08 Marks)

(c). Write short notes on network address translation (NAT).(06 Marks)


                                                  ***

