Fifth Semester B.E. Degree Examination, June/July 2013
        Computer Networks I

                PART-A

1(a).Explain OSI reference model.(10 Marks)

(b).Explain categories of network and differentiate between them.(10 Marks)

2(a).Represent the given sequence 01001110 in unipolar., NRZ-L, Manchesters, AMI, Pseudoternary?(06 Marks)

(b).The loss in a cable defined in debels/km (dB/km). If the signal at beginning of a cable with -3 dB/km has a power of 3 mW. What is the power of the signal at 5 km?

(c).Explain the PCM encoder.

3(a).Explain frequency hopping spread spectrum (FHSS).(10 Marks)

(b).Four 1 Kbps connections are multiplexed together. A unit is 1 bit. Find

 (i) The duration of 1 bit before multiplexing.
(ii) The transmission rate of the link.
(iii) The duration of a time slot.
(iv) The duration of a frame.(05 Marks)

(c). Differentiate between circuit switched, datagram networks and virtual circuit networks.(05 Marks)

4(a). Explain structure of encoder and decoder for hamming code.(08 Marks.)

(b). Find the codeword, using CRC given datavvord 1001 and generator 1011.(06 Marks)

(c). What is internet checksum? With an example, list the steps u.ndertaken by the sender and receiver for error detection.(06 Marks)

            PART-B

5(a).Explain stop-and-wait ARC protocol with neat diagram.(08 Marks)

(b).What is framing'? Explain bit and character stuffing with an example.(04 Marks)

(c).Write short not on HDLC.(08 Marks)

6(a).Explain CDMA.(06 Marks)

(b).A slotted ALOHA network transmits 200 bit frames using a shared channel with 200 Kbits/sec bandwidth. Find throughput if system produces

(i)1000 frames/sec
(ii) 500 frames/sec
(iii) Frames/sec.

(c).Explain 802.3 MAC frame format.

7(a).Explain the architecture of IEEE, 802.11.(10 Marks)

(b).Explain connecting devices.(10 Marks)

8(a).Draw IPV4 header format and explain.(08 Marks)

(b). A ISP is granted a block o r address starting with 190.100.0.0/16 (655, 536 address). The ISP needs to distribute these addressing to 3 groups of customers.

(i) First group has 64 customers each needs 256 address.
(ii) Second group has 12,8 customers each needs 128 address.
(iii) The third group has 128 customers each needs 64 address.
Design the subblock and findout. How many addresses are still available after their allocations?(07 Marks)

(c).Compare between IPV4 and IPV6.(05 Marks)

