 Fifth Semester B.E. Degree Examination, Dec. 2013.Jan 2014
    Computer Networks - I


             PART - A

1(a).What is data ccmununication'? List and expinin Ihi Cis corm ponent% of daut. communication system.(06 Marks)

(b).Discuss the ISO-OS1 'layered model, bringing out the functionalities of each layer.(10 Marks)

(c).Differentiate between:(04 Marks)

       i) ARP and RARP
       ii) UDP and TCP

2(a).Write a descriptive note on three causes of transmission impairment.(08 Marks)

(b).Explain the transmission modes?(06 Marks)

(c).Explain delta modulation.(06 Marks).

3(a).What is FDM? Briefly explain its multiplexing and demultiplexing process.(06 Marks)

(b). Four sources create 250 charades per second.The frame contain one character from each source and one extra bit for synchroni.mtion. Find

     i) The data rate of each source.
     ii) Duration of each character in each source
     iii)Frame rate
     iv) Duration of output frame
     v) Frame size in bits
     vi) Data rate of link. (06 Marks)

(c).What is time division multiplexing.? Explain how   statistical TDM overcomes disadvantages of synchronous TDM.(08 Marks)

4(a).Describe different types or errors,(03 Marks)

(b)Explain error detection and error correction with respect to block coding.(08 Marks)

(c). Find the codeword, using CRC given word "1001" and generator "1011".(09 Marks)

                  PART-B

5(a). Explain briefly, with neat figure stop and wait ARQ and Go Rack N ARQ. (12 marks)

(b). Explain the frame format and transitional phases of point to point protocol.(08 Marks)

6(a). Explain :(12 Marks)
            i) CSMA
            ii) CSMA/CD.

 (b).Describc 802.3 Mac frame. (08 Marks)

7(a). Explain IEEE 802.11  architecture.(10 Marks)

(b). Bring out thc differences between repeaters, bridges. routers and gateways.(10 Marks)

8(a). Explain with respect to IPV4. classful addressing and classless addressig.(10 Marks)

(b). Explain in detail IPV6 packet format.(10 Marks)

