 Seventh Semester 13.E. Degree Examination, December 2012
 Object Oriented Modeling and Design (OOMD)

         PART -A

1 a. What is object orientation? Explain its aspects with an example.(06 Marks)

(b).What is model? What are its advantages? Briefly discuss about three models.(08 Marks)

(c). What is generalization? Briefly discuss the generalization of equipments.(06 Marks)

2(a).Define the following terms. with an example

   (i) Enumerations
  (ii) Association ends
  (iii) Aggregation
  (iv) Abstract classes. (08 Marks)

(b).With respect to multiple inheritance, briefly discuss about

 (i) Multiple classification
 (ii) Workarounds.(06 Marks)

(c).What do you mean by states and events? Draw the state diagram for a telephone line system.(06 Marks)

3(a).What is concurrency? Explain the aggregation concurrency, with an example.(06 Marks)

(b).What are sequence models? Draw the sequence model for oil — line stock. broker system.(06 Marks)

(c).Briefly discuss the usecase relationships and draw the usecase diagram of stock brokerage system.(08 Marks)

4(a).Briefly discuss the software development stages.(08 Marks)

(b).Identify the classes for ATM bark system. What criteria would you take into consideration to select right classes? Explain.(08 Marks)

(c).List the steps to construct domain state model.(04 Marks)

         PART — B

5(a).With a neat activity diagram, explain the card verification activity of ATM bank system.(06 Marks)

(b).Define the following terms

(i) Libraries (ii) Frameworks
 (iii) Patterns.   (06 Marks)

(c).Explain the steps in designing a compiler by using batch transformation.(08 Marks)

6(a).Briefly discuss the design optimization and explain its tasks, with an example.(08 Marks)

(b).List and explain the steps involved in organizing of a class design.(06 Marks)

(c).Differentiate between forward engineering and reverse engineering.(06 Marks)

7(a).What is a pattern? Explain the model — view controller design for software architecture, with OMT diagram.(06 Marks)

(b).Explain the client — dispatcher — design pattern.(08 Marks)

(c).List and explain different pattern categories.(06 Marks)

8(a).Explain the command processor design pattern.(08 Marks)

(b).What are idioms and styles? Explain with the help of an example, a style guide idiom. (06 Marks)

(c).Explain the publisher — subscriber design pattern.(06 Marks)

            *****
