 Seventh Semester B.E. Degree Examination, June/July 2014

 Object-Oriented Modelling and Design

     PART — A

1(a).With respect to objected oriented modeling and design, explain the concept of 00 themes.(06 Marks)

(b).Explain the three models useful to model a system and the relationship among them.(08 Marks)

(c).Using the class diagram given below, prepare an object diagram for the two triangles with a common side under the following condition:

 (i)    A point belongs to exactly one polygon.
 (ii) A point belongs to one or more polygon.(06 Marks)
                      _________
               3...* | Point   |
    POLYGON----------| x coord |
            {order}  | y coord |
                     |_________|

 Fig.Q.1(c) Class diagram for polygon and point

2(a).A simple digital watch has a display and two buttons to set it, the A button, and the B button.
 The watch has two modes of operation, display time, set time in the display time mode, the watch displays hours and minutes, separated by a flashing colon.
The set time mode has two submodes, set hours, set minutes. The botton A selects modes.
Each time it is pressed, the mode advances in the sequence: display, set hours, set minutes,display etc. Within the submodes the button B advances the hours or minutes once each time it is pressed.
Buttons must be released before they can generate another event. Prepare a state diagram of the watch. (08 Marks)

(b).What is an event? Explain the different types of events with example for each one. (06 Marks)

(c).Explain the following:
(i)    Aggregation vs association.


(ii) Aggregation vs composition.(06 Marks)

3(a).What do you mean by concurrency? Explain the different types of concurrency among objects.(08 Marks)

(b).What are the guidelines for sequence models?(06 Marks)

(c).Explain the concept of swim lanes used in activity diagram with a simple example for servicing an airplane.(06 Marks)

4(a).Explain the sequence of well-defined development stages of a software development process.(10 Marks)

(b).What steps are performed in constructing a domain state model?(10 Marks)

            PART — B

5(a).With the help of activity diagram, show the possible responses for the verification of card inserted by the user at the ATM.(08 Marks)

(b).Flow are global resources handled while designing a system and how are boundary conditions handled?(12 Marks)

6.Write short notes on:

   a. Recursing downwards.(04 Marks)
   b. Two-way associations.(06 Marks)
   c. Reverse engineering vs forward engineering.(06 Marks)
   d. Wrapping.(04 Marks)

7(a).What is a pattern? What makes a pattern? What are its properties?(10 Marks)

(b).Explain the client-dispatcher-server pattern following the pattern template.(10 Marks)

8(a).Explain the view handler management pattern.(10 Marks)

(b).What is an Idiom? Explain how is the counted pointer Idiom makes memory management easier.(10 Marks)


            *****






