Seventh Sem- Degree Examination, Dec.2014/Jan.2015
 Programming the Web

    PART — A

1(a).What is web browser and web server? Explain how communication takes place in between web browser and web server.(07 Marks)

(b).What is the purpose of a MIME type specification in a request/response transaction between a browser and a server?(05 Marks)

(c).Explain how the text content of XHTML document can be formatted with XHTML tags with suitable examples.(08 Marks)

2(a).Which widgets are created with the <input> tag? Explain with examples.(08 Marks)

(b).Briefly explain the different selector forms of the CSS. Illustrate the use of each with suitable example.(12 Marks)

3(a).Describe briefly the major differences between Java and JavaScript.(04 Marks)

(b).Describe the two ways an Array object can be created. Explain the Array methods with suitable example for each.(12 Marks)

(c).Write a Javascript to generate first 4 Fibonacci numbers.(04 Marks)

4(a).Explain the basic concepts of event handling. List the events and their tag attribute.(12 Marks)

(b).What is a dynamic XHTML document? How positioning and moving of elements are done in dynamic XHTML?(08 Marks)

5(a).Explain the four possible keywords used in a DTD declaration.(10 Marks)

(b).Create a DTD for a catalog of cars, where each car has the child elements make, model, year, color, engine, numbers-of-doors, transmission type and accessories .The engine element has child elements number of cylinders and fuel system. The accessories element has the attributes radio, air-conditioning, power-windowos and power-brakes, each of which is required and has the possible values yes and no. Entities must be declared for the names of popular car makes.(10 Marks)

6(a).Briefly describe string functions of perl with suitable example.(05 Marks)

(b).Write a perl program to read three numbers a, b and c, each on its own -line, from the keyboard and return the value of the expression loab-[[c-1] / 17.44] (06 Marks)

(c).What is a query string? What is the format of a query string that has multiple widget data values?How is a query String transmitted to the server with get method?(09 Marks)

7(a).Explain the actions of the implode and explode functions.(03 Marks)

(b).Describe how files are created, read and write on the server system using PHP.(12 Marks)

(c).What is cookie? How it can be created in a PHP script?(05 Marks)

8.Write a short notes on:(5X4=20)

 a.Ruby.
 b.Rail.
 c.Data access with perl and MYSQL.
 d.Document object model.
